Benjamin D. Killeen

Ph.D. Student, Johns Hopkins University Department of Computer Science 3400 N Charles St Baltimore, MD 21218, USA killeen@jhu.edu

With Gordon Kindlmann.

😭 benjamindkilleen.com - 🚢 arcade.cs.jhu.edu - 🚢 cirl.lcsr.jhu.edu

 Вепјатіп D. Killeen - № 0000-0003-2511-7929 - ♠ benjamindkilleen

 🎔 @bdkilleen - 🛅 benjamindkilleen - 🔟 @benjamindkilleen

Summary

A Ph.D. Student at Johns Hopkins University, I am interested in intelligent surgical systems that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves realistic simulation of interventional X-ray imaging for the purpose of developing Al-integrated surgical systems. I am a member of the Advanced Robotics and Computationally Augmented Environments (ARCADE) research group and the Computational Interaction and Robotics Laboratory (CIRL).

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 08/2019 - present With Mathias Unberath and Gregory D. Hager. B.A., Computer Science with Honors, Minor in Physics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA. 09/2015 - 06/2019

Academic Experience

Research assistant, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 08/2020 - present With Mathias Unberath, Gregory D. Hager. Research Assistant, Laboratory for Computational Sensing and Robotics, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, 08/2019 - 06/2020 With Gregory D. Hager, Mathias Unberath, and Russel Taylor. Research assistant, Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA. 03/2018 - 08/2019 With Gordon Kindlmann.

Professional Experience

Computer Vision / Al Intern, Applied Research, Intuitive Surgical Inc., Sunnyvale, CA, USA. 06/2020 - 07/2020 With Omid Mohareri. Software Development Intern, Cognitive Computing, Epic Systems, Verona, WI, USA. 06/2018 - 08/2018 06/2017 - 08/2017 Research Intern, IBM Research - Almaden, San Jose, CA, USA. With Geoffrey Burr.

Selected Honors

Link Foundation Fellowship in Modeling, Simulation, and Training Proposal: Interactive Digital Twins for Simulating the Future of Work in Al- and Robot-assisted Operating Nominated, Intuitive/IPCAI Bench to Bedside Award 06/2023 For paper [J-5] at IPCAI 2023.

06/2023

02/2022

05/2020

Runner-up, Physics of Medical Imaging Best Student Paper Award For paper [C-5] at SPIE Medical Imaging 2022.

Best Paper Award in Bioengineering 10/2021 For paper [C-4] at IEEE BIBE 2021.

Best Presentation Award 04/2021 In Reliable Software Systems at Johns Hopkins University.

Best Graduate Project Award In Computer Integrated Surgical Systems and Technology II at Johns Hopkins University.

COVID-19 Dataset Award, Kaggle	04/2020
For the dataset in [M-1].	

ı	ntuitive Surgical Best Project Award.		12/2019

For Enriching Unsupervised Feature Learning via Intermediate Subtasks in Deep Learning at Johns Hopkins

2019 - 2020 LCSR Fellowship for Outstanding Incoming Ph.D. Students, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.

Services and Leadership		
Academic Services	President , LCSR Graduate Student Association at Johns Hopkins University. Established an executive board, annual operating budget, and election process.	08/2022 - present
	Sports Officer, MICCAI Society Student Board. Head of Student Resources, LCSR Graduate Student Committee at Johns Hopkins University.	12/2021 - present 09/2020 - 08/2022
Community	Family Member, Thread, Baltimore, MD, USA. Volunteer Instructor, CompileHer, Chicago, IL, USA.	06/2021 - 2022 2019
Peer Review	Computer Assisted Surgery (CAS) International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) Medical Imaging Computing and Computer Aided Interventions (MICCAI) Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR) IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI) IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L) International Symposium on Medical Robotics (ISMR) International Conference on Information Processing in Computer-Assisted Interventions (IPCAI)	2023
	MICCAI Educational Challenge Medical Image Analysis IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)	2022
	IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)	2021
	Nature Scientific Data	2020
Supervision		
Graduate Students	Fanghao Cheng, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	05/2023 - present
	Shreayan Chaudhary, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	05/2023 - present
	Han Zhang, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	01/2023 - present
	Aditya Kulkarni, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	09/2022 - present
	Qiyuan Wu, Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now a PhD student at Cornell University.	08/2022 - 06/2023
	Zidi Tao , Research Assistant, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now a PhD student at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute.	10/2021 - 06/2022
	Shreya Chakraborty , Masters, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now at PathAI.	08/2020 - 09/2021
	Philipp Nikutta , Visiting Masters, Technical University of Munich, Munich, Germany. Now at Argo AI.	12/2019 - 03/2020
Undergraduates	Liam Wang, Bachelors, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	01/2022 - present
	Sambhav Chordia, Bachelors, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	06/2022 - 12/2022
	Sean Sebastian Darcy, Bachelors, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Now a PhD student at California Institute of Technology.	10/2021 - 10/2022
	Nethra Venkatayogi , Bachelors, The University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX, USA. Now a PhD student at JHU with Muyinatu Bell.	05/2021 - 10/2021
	Max Judish, Bachelors, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.	01/2021 - 08/2021
Student Projects	Recreating Pelvic Trauma Surgery in Virtual Reality for the Development of Novel C-arm Interfaces Han Zhang, Zixuan Liu, Liam Wang. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins Unviersity Honored with the audience Best Project Poster Award.	2023
	Making 2D/3D Registration Accessible Jiaming Zhang, Zhangcong She. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins Unviersity. Python library available from PyPI and GitHub.	2023
	3D Segmentation of Hard and Soft Tissue for Simulating X-ray Image Formation with Deep Learning Qiyuan Wu, Zhiyuan Ding, Sean Darcy. Computer Integrated Surgery II, Johns Hopkins University.	2022

With Russ Taylor.

Wrote supplementary course material, led weekly office hours, and taught regular discussion sections.

Computer Integrated Surgery, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD,

With Russ Taylor and Emad Boctor.

Held weekly office hours and biweekly discussion sections. Managed grading together with Maia Stiber.

Machine Learning and Large Scale Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA.

With Yali Amit.

Wrote supplementary course material and held weekly lab sessions. Graded coursework.

Selected review: "Ben was incredibly patient during office hours and always responsive to student questions. In addition, he often presented demos during office hours or showed easier ways to handle the homework assignments; both were very helpful."

More reviews available at benjamindkilleen.com/teaching/2019-spring-lsda

Teaching Services

Course assistant. Department of Computer Science, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA

01/2019 - 08/2019

Sprina 2019

- Scientific Visualization
- Introduction to Computer Science I
- Introduction to Computer Science II

Tutoring in Computer Science, Machine Learning, Baltimore, MD, USA.

06/2020 - 08/2022

J-6

J-5

J-4

1-3

1-2

J-1

C - 6

C - 4

C-3

C-2

Worked with middle and high school students.

Publications

I have first- (co-) authored 7 (4) peer-reviewed papers and 2 (0) preprints. My publication list is also available on Google Scholar. (*) denotes equal contribution.

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles

- **B.D. Killeen**, S.M. Cho, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, M. Unberath. In Silico simulation: A key enabling technology for next-generation intelligent surgical systems. Progress in Biomedical Engineering, 2023. doi: 10.1088/2516-1091/acd28b.
- **B.D. Killeen**, C. Gao, K. Oguine, S. Darcy, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, G. Osgood, M. Unberath. An autonomous X-ray image acquisition and interpretation system for assisting percutaneous pelvic fracture fixation. International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery, 1–8, 2023. doi: 10.1007/s11548-023-02941-
- Nominated for the Intuitive/IPCAI Bench to Bedside Award.
- C. Gao, **B.D. Killeen**, Y. Hu, R.B. Grupp, R.H. Taylor, M. Armand, M. Unberath. Synthetic data accelerates the development of generalizable learning-based algorithms for X-ray image analysis. Nature Machine Intelligence, Mar. 2023, pp. 1–15, doi: 10.1038/s42256-023-00629-1.
- **B. D. Killeen**, J. Winter, W. Gu, A. Martin-Gomez, R. H. Taylor, G. Osgood, M. Unberath. Mixed reality interfaces for achieving desired views with robotic X-ray systems. Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering: Imaging & Visualization, 7 Dec. 2022, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.1080/21681163.2022.2154272.
- Special issue: Augmented Environments for Computer Assisted Interventions (AE-CAI) 2022.
- A. Hundt, **B. Killeen**, H. Kwon, C. Paxton, GD Hager. "Good Robot!": Efficient Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Step Visual Tasks with Sim to Real Transfer. IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 5, no. 4, pp. 6724–6731, Oct. 2020. doi: 10.1109/LRA.2020.3015448.
- S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, R. M. Shelby, I. Boybat, C. di Nolfo, S. Sidler, M. Giordano, M. Bodini, N. Farinha, **B. Killeen**, C. Cheng, Y. Jaoudi, G. W. Burr. Equivalent-accuracy accelerated neural-network training using analogue memory. Nature, vol. 558, no. 7708, p. 60, Jun. 2018. doi: 10.1038/s41586-018-0180-5.

Peer-reviewed Conference Papers

- **B. D. Killeen**, H. Zhang, J. Mangulabnan, M. Armand, R.H. Taylor, G. Osgood, and M. Unberath, Pelphix: Surgical Phase Recognition from X-ray Images in Percutaneous Pelvic Fixation. To appear: International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention, 2023. arXiv:2304.09285.
- **B. D. Killeen**, Shreya Chakraborty, Greg Osgood, Mathias Unberath. Toward perception-based anticipation of cortical breach during K-wire fixation of the pelvis. Medical Imaging 2022: Physics of Medical Imaging. SPIE. doi: 10.1117/12.2612989.
- Runner-up, SPIE Medical Imaging Physics of Medical Imaging Best Student Paper Award
- J. D. Opfermann*, B. D. Killeen*, C. Bailey, M. Khan, A. Uneri, K. Suzuki, M. Armand, F. Hui, A. Krieger**, M. Unberath**. Feasibility of a Cannula-mounted Piezo Robot for Image-guided Vertebral Augmentation: Toward a Low Cost, Semi-autonomous Approach. 2021 IEEE 21st International Conference on Bioinformatics and Bioengineering (BIBE), Kragujevac, Serbia, 2021 pp. 1-8. doi: 10.1109/BIBE52308.2021.9635356.
- *Joint first authors; ** joint last authors.
- Honored with Best Paper Award in Bioengineering.
- X. Liu*, B. D. Killeen*, A. Sinha, M. Ishii, G. Hager, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Neighborhood Normalization for Robust Geometric Feature Learning. Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, 2021.
- C. Gao, X. Liu, W. Gu, **B. D. Killeen**, M. Armand, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Generalizing Spatial Transformers to Projective Geometry with Applications to 2D/3D Registrationc. International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention, 2020, arxiv:2003.10987.

	X. Liu, Y. Zhang, B. Killeen , M. Ishii, G. Hager, R. Taylor, M. Unberath. Extremely Dense Point Correspondences using a Learned Feature Descriptor. Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pp. 4847-4856, 2020.	C-1
Preprints	J. Y. Wu*, B. D. Killeen *, P. Nikutta, M. Thies, A. Zapaishchykova, S. Chakraborty, M. Unberath. Changes in Reproductive Rate of SARS-CoV-2 Due to Non-pharmaceutical Interventions in 1,417 U.S. Counties. medRxiv preprint, Jun. 2020, doi: 10.1101/2020.05.31.20118687.	M-2
	B. D. Killeen*, J. Y. Wu*, K. Shah, A. Zapaishchykova, P. Nikutta, A. Tamhane, S. Chakraborty, J. Wei, T. Gao, M. Thies, M. Unberath. A County-level Dataset for Informing the United States' Response to COVID-19. arXiv preprint, 2020, arXiv:2004.00756.	M-1
Patents	G. W. Burr and B. D. Killeen . 2020. Efficient Processing of Convolutional Neural Network Layers Using Analog-memory-based Hardware. 20200117986, filed March 25, 2019, and issued April 16, 2020, uspto.report/patent/app/20200117986.	P-1
Selected Press	Patterson, Jaimie. PhD student awarded Link Foundation Fellowship Johns Hopkins Department of Computer Science. The John Hopkins University, May 24, 2023. https://www.cs.jhu.edu/news/phd-student-awarded-link-foundation-fellowship/.	2023
	Graham, Catherine. "Synthetic Data for Al Outperform Real Data in Robot-Assisted Surgery." The Johns Hopkins University Hub. The Johns Hopkins University, March 20, 2023. hub.jhu.edu/2023/03/20/synthetic-data-outperform-real-data-robot-assisted-surgery/.	2023
	Dziarkach, Andrei. "Details with Andrei Dziarkach." Voice of America. November 21, 2020 Accessed November 26, 2020. golosameriki.com/a/detali/5671254.html.	2020
	Rosen, Jill. "Dog Training Methods Help JHU Teach Robots to Learn New Tricks." The Johns Hopkins University Hub. The Johns Hopkins University, October 26, 2020. hub.jhu.edu/2020/10/26/positive-reinforcement-for-robots	
Selected Coursework		
Graduate	Vision as Bayesian Inference Reliable Software Systems Theory of Computation Parallel Programming Nonlinear Optimization II Computer Integrated Surgery II Computer Integrated Surgery I Deep Learning	GPA: 3.82
Undergraduate	Unsupervised Learning* Computer Vision Machine Learning and Large Scale Data Analysis Operating Systems Honors Combinatorics Honors Algorithms Honors Discrete Mathematics Scientific Visualization Programming Languages Networks and Distributed Systems Quantum Mechanics I \& II Intermediate Mechanics Electronics Wizards *Graduate level.	GPA: 3.81
Memberships	International Society for Optics and Photonics (SPIE) Student Member Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Graduate Student Member	
Extracurricular	In my free time, I enjoy bouldering, cycling, and running. I am an avid fan of art museums, and I write creatively: Creative nonfiction: benjamindkilleen.com/blog Science fiction.	
Metadata	This document is available - online: benjamindkilleen.com/markdown-cv.	

- as a PDF: benjamindkilleen.com/files/cv.pdf.

Created based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp.

MIT License.

Last updated: May 2023